Whiting, Indiana: Generational Memory 1991-1993 ohrc102
Center for Documentary Research and Practice
Whiting, Indiana: Generational Memory
1991-1993
Center for Documentary Research and Practice
Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory
ohrc102
88 Interviews Audio files, transcripts, and collateral materials
This collection of interviews primarily delves into the Republican view of Indiana politics from the nineteen twenties to the early nineteen sixties. Major emphasis is placed on both state and national elections and conventions from 1940-1948. The project contains discussions of political campaigns (including finances), the patronage system, and legislation battles. The interviews also reflect on William Jenner by describing his character, beliefs, and influence on Republican politics in Indiana.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains eighty-eight interviews conducted over three years. All interviews consist of audio tapes and some have typed transcripts.
Acquisition Information
Oral history interviews conducted by the Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory from 1968 to the present, with particular focus on the history of twentieth-century America and the Midwest.
- Anonymous, July 21, 1991; 91-037; Orr, Elisabeth; 37 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 97 minutes; no index
  Access Status
  Restricted: Contact center staff for more information
  Scope and Content Note
  In this interview, the interviewee relates stories of prejudice, discrimination, and racism aimed at Mexicans, African-Americans, and other minorities in Whiting, Indiana. Also described are the interviewee's family values, the traditional political party affiliation of the interviewee's family and ethnic group, and the nepotism rampant in the hiring practices of many Whiting employers. In addition, generational differences regarding divorce and the interviewee's opinion of the Vietnam War and the welfare system are discussed.
  discrimination; divorce; Education; family values; minority groups; nepotism; political party affiliation; racism; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; welfare; work ethic
- Anonymous, August 14, 1991; 91-047; Bodnar, John; 28 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 60 minutes; index
  In this interview, the interviewee discusses his family history, his life in Whiting, Indiana, and the deterioration of America and its values that has occurred over the years. He speaks of Slovak immigration and the Slovak community in Whiting, as well as the downside of Standard Oil: unethical work and business practices. In addition, he speaks of the increasing diversity of the area and the artifacts of popular culture he has accumulated from the early twentieth century.
  emigration; ethnic diversity; family values; local artifacts; Mexican-Americans; nepotism; popular culture; sex; Slovak community; unethical labor practices; Standard Oil Company; Westville Hospital
- Belshaw, William, February 24, 1992; 91-147; Berry, Chad; 24 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 60 minutes; index
  Open
  William Belshaw, an Indiana native, attended DePauw University and later, Northwestern University School of Law. After spending some time in Illinois, he settled down in Whiting, Indiana, where he worked as an attorney, and eventually, a labor arbitrator. Mr. Belshaw discusses his family history, his work experiences, and his thoughts about how America has changed since World War II.
  attorney; labor arbitrator; Lowell, Indiana; ethnic diversity; labor arbitration; law practice; Rector's Scholarship; Religion; World War II; DePauw University; National Academy of Arbitrators; Northwestern University School of Law; Standard Oil Company; United States. Navy
- Boyle, Austin, November 1, 1991; 91-145; Klemm, Verda; 26 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 80 minutes; index
  Austin Boyle spent his childhood and the majority of his adult life in Whiting, Indiana. He discusses what Whiting was like during his childhood, his college experiences, and his jobs as a reporter and as a public relations officer for a bank. Mr. Boyle also tells of his experiences in the United States Air Force during World War II. Finally, he shares his thoughts on politics, religion, and family values.
  attendance officer; intelligence officer; newspaper reporter; Chicago, Illinois; Mexico; New Orleans, Louisiana; St. Petersburg, Florida; Texas; D-Day; family values; Great Depression; local politics; Mardi Gras; petroleum coke; Prohibition; Religion; unions; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; World War II; Chicago Daily News; Inland Steel; The New Orleans Item; New Orleans Times-Picayune; Notre Dame University; Standard Oil Company; United States Air Force; Frierson; Gore; Alferez, Enrique; Hemingway, Ernest; Truman, Harry S.
- Brown, George, November 28, 1990; 91-010; Dabertin, David; 31 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 73 minutes; index
  George Brown spent the majority of his life in Whiting, Indiana. He discusses the state of the city during several time periods, including World War I, the Great Depression, and World War II. After operating a gas station, Mr. Brown went to work for Standard Oil. He speaks of this company's impact on the town and about his work experiences there.
  factory worker; gas station owner; Gary, Indiana; 1955 Standard Oil fire; air quality; courtship; films; Germans; Great Depression; Marriage; Prohibition; saloons; streetcars; tower stills; unions; United States Civil War; vacations; World War I; World War II; AMOCO; Fraternal Order of Masons; Indiana University; Lambda Chi Alpha; Standard Oil Company; Schrage; Carmichael, Hoagy, 1899-1981; Nichols, Ed
- Brummett, Charles, April 9, 1992; 91-164; Berry, Chad; 35 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 94 minutes; index
  Charles Brummett moved to Whiting, Indiana from Tennessee in 1960 to find work. He talks about his experiences during World War II and how it changed him. Mr. Brummett also discusses the South and desegregation, including his own perspectives and personal biases. Finally, Brummett talks about how the United States has changed over the years, concluding that the separation of church and state, legalized abortion, and increased drug use have ruined the family values he fought for on the beaches of Normandy.
  factory worker; Tennessee; African-Americans; desegregation; family values; farming; local politics; school prayer; unions; World War II; United States Army
- Cheatham, John; Cheatham, Opal, July 28, 1991; 91-041; Orr, Lisa; 46 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 96 minutes; index
  John and Opal Cheatham discuss their migration to Whiting, Indiana from the South, their family, the importance of religion in their lives, and their experiences during World War II. In addition, the Cheathams comment on their family values, local employment and the local economy, and local politics.
  cosmotologist; dispatcher; foreman; African-Americans; child discipline; family values; labor strikes; local economy; local politics; Religion; unions; World War II; Lever Brothers; Rand McNally; Standard Oil Company
- Coppi, Jan, June 4, 1991; 91-138; Dabertin, David; 30 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 72 minutes; index
  Jan Coppi recalls his childhood, education, and family in Whiting, Indiana. He speaks of local employment and his particular employers, in addition to his local participation in such recreational activities as baseball and hunting.
  dental technician; exterminator; factory worker; fire fighter; Wolf Lake, Indiana; baseball; Education; hunting; local business; local schools; mining; Television; Clark High School; Hoosier Theater; Inland Steel; Lever Brothers
- Corpus, Maggie, May 14, 1991; 91-029; Berry, Chad; 36 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 75 minutes; index
  Maggie Corpus moved with her family to Whiting, Indiana in 1974. She primarily discusses her parents, her childhood, her brothers and sisters, and her own family. She also talks about her work and social experiences in Whiting, particularly focusing on the prejudice she faced as a Mexican American.
  secretary; East Chicago, Illinois; discrimination; Education; family values; hillbillies; housework; local politics; materialism; Mexican-Americans; Inland Steel; Uñate
- Curosh, Delores; Curosh, William; DeLuca, Bertha; DeLuca, Michael, March 2, 1992; 91-151; Bodnar, John; 87 pages; 3 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 150 minutes; index
  William and Delores Curosh and Michael and Bertha DeLuca all spent major portions of their adult lives in Whiting, Indiana. Although they primarily discuss their lives in this town, they also talk about their childhoods and families, their lives in Arizona after they left Indiana, and how the country has changed. With regard to their years in Whiting, the Curoshes and DeLucas discuss what it was like raising their families in the community, their employment in Whiting, attitudes toward immigrants there, and religious and political issues within the town.
  electrician; store owner; Arizona; Czechoslovakia; Germany; Philippines; Catholicism; credit cards; emigration; family finances; Fourth of July; Great Depression; Greek-Americans; Mexican-Americans; local airport; local crime; local politics; pollution; Religion; still cleaning; World War II; American Trust and Savings Bank; Standard Oil Company; St. John's Catholic Church; Truman, Harry S.
- Dabertin, David, October 11, 1991; 91-141; Bodnar, John; 39 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 80 minutes; index
  David Dabertin, an environmental attorney, grew up in Whiting, Indiana, and continued to live in the area during his adult life. Mr. Dabertin discusses the environmental contamination and pollution in Whiting and how and when this occurred. He also speaks of the companies involved in this contamination and their practices regarding their employees. Finally, Mr. Dabertin talks about his family, his childhood in Whiting, and how much the town has changed.
  environmental attorney; Grand Calumet River, Indiana; Lake Michigan; Catholicism; conservation; drinking water; drugs; George Lake landfill; lead poisoning; local politics; pollution; state environmental controls; water filtration; AMOCO; Calumet College; Federated Metals; Indiana University. School of Public and Environmental Affairs; Society of the Precious Blood; Standard Oil Company; St. John's Catholic Church; United Citizens Association
- Dado, Joseph; Dado, Betty, July 20, 1991; 91-036; Orr, Elisabeth; 57 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 90 minutes; index
  Joe Dado grew up in Whiting, Indiana; his wife Betty Dado moved there as a teenager. They remained in Whiting and raised their family there. Mr. and Mrs. Dado primarily speak of their childhoods, their children and grandchildren, and the values and beliefs that are important to them. They briefly discuss how Whiting and its populace have changed over the years and they compare Whiting to Gary, Indiana.
  clerk; factory supervisor; mechanic; Gary, Indiana; Hammond, Indiana; 1991 Persian Gulf War; divorce; family values; Great Depression; local employment; local politics; parochial schools; Religion; unions; welfare; work ethic; World War II; Whiting Community Center
- Dewey, Marge, July 30, 1991; 91-044; Klemm, Verda; 19 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 36 minutes; index
  In this brief interview, Marge Dewey discusses her life and memories of Whiting, Indiana, including the impact of World War II and the Vietnam War on her life and on Whiting. She speaks of the importance of religion to her life, and comments on local business and the relations among different ethnic groups in Whiting.
  community life; ethnic diversity; local business; Religion; unions; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; World War II; Whiting News; Women's Army Corps; Chrustowski, Stanley; Williamson, Eddie
- Dominiak, Mark; Dominiak, Roberta, April 8, 1992; 91-162; Berry, Chad; 39 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 90 minutes; index
  Mark and Roberta Dominiak, long time residents of Whiting, Indiana, describe their memories and perceptions of their childhoods, families, education in local schools, the local economy, and their family values. Roberta Dominiak, a Mexican American, recalls some of the discrimination and harassment she and her family have experienced in Whiting. In addition, the Dominiaks describe community life, the problems posed by the possible introduction of a local airport, and the increasing demographic diversification of the area.
  East Chicago, Illinois; Laredo, Texas; advertising; community life; ethnic diversity; family values; local airport; local economy; local schools; Mexican-Americans; Immaculate Conception Catholic School
- Dryjanski, Joann; Dryjanski, Raymond, May 14, 1991; 91-031; Berry, Chad; 39 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 87 minutes; index
  Joann Dryjanski, born on March 28, 1932, and her husband, Raymond Dryjanski, born on April 3, 1918, discuss their lives in Whiting, Indiana, their employment histories, the increased crime rate in recent years, and the increase in local unemployment. Mrs. Dryjanski recalls her first marriage and the foreign mission work she did in Japan at that time. Mr. Dryjanski speaks a little of his service during World War II and his memories of the Great Depression. In addition, the couple speaks of the ethnic diversity and different neighborhoods of Whiting.
  Hammond, Indiana; Japan; Robertsdale, Indiana; ethnic diversity; family values; foreign mission work; Great Depression; local crime; local employment; steel mills; World War II; Civilian Conservation Corps
- Dudzik, Helen, February 10, 1991; 91-019; Dabertin, David; 33 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 72 minutes; index
  Helen Dudzik, born on November 17, 1916, is a lifelong resident of Whiting, Indiana who recalls her childhood, family, personal employment history, and education in this interview. She speaks of the ethnic de facto segregation that characterized Whiting in her youth, and of other memories, including those of dime stores, home births, the Standard Oil fire of 1955, Roman Catholicism, the prominence of church youth organizations, and World War II. She also discusses local employment, crime, pollution, and changes over the years.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Hammond, Indiana; 1955 Standard Oil fire; Catholicism; church youth activities; community changes; dime stores; ethnic diversity; home births; local crime; local employment; local politics; Polish immigrants; pollution; steel mills; World War II; Standard Oil Company
- Dvorscak, Agnes; Dvorscak, John, March 12, 1991; May 14, 1991; 91-021; Bodnar, John; 48 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 90 minutes; index
  John Dvorscak, born in 1905, and his wife Agnes Dvorscak, born in 1912, discuss their lives in and memories of Whiting, Indiana, including local employment at Standard Oil Company, church-centered community life, the Great Depression, and the increasing materialism of recent years. Mr. Dvorscak describes the cleaning of tower stills at Standard Oil, his activities with industrial baseball teams in the nineteen twenties, job safety, wages, and the cost of living. In addition, the Dvorscaks discuss pollution, local politics, the increase in the area's population of Mexican-Americans, candle workers, and the popular pastimes of attending vaudeville productions and going to the movies. Mr. Dvorscak also speaks of his family's emigration from Austria-Hungary, in which they walked to Bremen, Germany and took a ship to Ellis Island.
  Ellis Island, New York; community changes; community life; cost of living; emigration; films; Great Depression; industrial baseball teams; job safety; local employment; local politics; materialism; Mexican-Americans; pollution; still cleaning; vaudeville; wages; women workers; Standard Oil Company; Willkie, Wendell L.
- Etter, Donald, April 8, 1992; 91-161; Berry, Chad; 21 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 60 minutes; index
  Donald Etter, born on February 24, 1952, discusses his views on political, religious, and marital commitment, as well as his difficulty completing projects and processes that are of little interest to him. He speaks of religion in general, of the Baptist, Pentecostal, and Catholic faiths, and of his recreational drug and alcohol use in the context of religious restrictions against such activities. In addition, Mr. Etter discusses his ex-wife, his marriage and divorce, and his relationship with his parents.
  alcohol; Catholicism; drug testing; marijuana; Marriage; Pentecostal faith; recreational drug use; Southern Baptist Church; women's movement; Fraternal Order of Masons; Whiting Baptist Church
- Etter, Donald, May 15, 1991; 91-032; Berry, Chad; 32 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 87 minutes; index
  Donald Etter, born on February 24, 1952, recalls his childhood and life in Whiting, Indiana as the son of Southerners who migrated to the area. He speaks of the benefits of employment at AMOCO, of the ethnic segregation and discrimination that characterized Whiting (decreasingly over the decades since the nineteen seventies), and the religious practices associated with the Southern Baptist Church. In addition, Mr. Etter discusses local politics, the increasing emphasis on environmental pollution, the strength and importance of labor unions, and drug use and experimentation.
  Kentucky; 1955 Standard Oil fire; discrimination; drugs; ethnic diversity; political party affiliation; pollution; religious practices; Southern Baptist Church; unions; AMOCO; Culver Military Academy; More, Albert
- Etter, James; Etter, Sara, June 25, 1992; 91-171; Berry, Chad; 46 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 115 minutes; index
  James Etter, born in 1927, and his wife Sara Etter, born on August 29, 1930, discuss their respective families and childhoods, especially during the Great Depression, their marriage, and moving north to Whiting, Indiana to find work after Mr. Etter's service in World War II. They discuss setting up their home in Whiting, and the local industry, ethnic diversity and discrimination, air pollution, community life and social ties, and the local economy there. In addition, the Etters discuss being labeled as Southern "hillbillies" in Whiting, and their deep commitment to the Whiting Baptist Church.
  Kentucky; La Havre, France; community life; discrimination; ethnic diversity; Great Depression; local economy; local industry; pollution; rural life; unions; World War II; Hartford Baptist Church; Standard Forge; Standard Oil Company; Whiting Baptist Church; Works Progress Administration
- Flores, José; Flores, Estela, May 14, 1991; 91-027; Berry, Chad; 43 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 85 minutes; index
  José Flores, born on May 1, 1925, and his wife, Estela Flores, born on October 6, 1928, recall their childhoods and families in Mexico and Texas, respectively, their emigration to the United States, and the life they made for themselves in Whiting, Indiana. The discuss the discrimination they experienced as Mexican-Americans, the increase in the Mexican population of Whiting over the years, the work ethic and family values they transmitted and emphasized to their children, and Mr. Flores' membership in the steel workers' union.
  Mexico; child discipline; discrimination; emigration; family values; Mexican-Americans; women's movement; work ethic; Inland Steel; United Steelworkers of America; Peña, Raymond
- Frankowski, Clementine, August 14, 1991; 91-046; Bodnar, John; 33 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 79 minutes; index
  Clementine Frankowski, born in 1906, discusses her parents' emigration from Poland, her siblings' diseases and deaths before the advent of antibiotics and modern medicine, and her career as a physician in Whiting, Indiana. Dr. Frankowski speaks of her years in medical school at Loyola University, her medical practice in Whiting, and the sexism she experienced at hospitals such as St. Catherine's. In addition, she comments on how her Catholicism impacted her medical practice, especially in the area of birth control.
  physician; birth control; cancer; Catholicism; diseases; medical practice; medical school; national politics; poverty; racial diversity; sexism; St. Catherine's Hospital; Standard Oil Company
- Gehrke, Betty, September 28, 1990; 91-004; Bodnar, John; 27 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 73 minutes; index
  Born in 1911, Betty Gehrke discusses her parents, and her memories of World War I and World War II, including V-E Day and V-J Day. She recalls the 1955 Standard Oil fire and the immediate reactions of the Whiting community to the disaster. In addition, she speaks of the impact television had on daily life and comments on life during the Great Depression. Mrs. Gehrke also discusses pollution, racial diversity, and local politics in Whiting.
  homemaker; librarian; 1955 Standard Oil fire; community life; gender roles; Great Depression; hoboes; local politics; pollution; racial diversity; racism; Television; V-E Day; V-J Day; World War I; World War II; Plymouth Congregational Church; Standard Oil Company
- Gehrke, Clarence; Gehrke, Betty, October 11, 1991; 91-142; Bodnar, John; 51 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 86 minutes; index
  Clarence Gehrke, born in 1909, and his wife, Betty Gehrke, discuss their families and childhoods, and the life they made together in Whiting, Indiana. Much of the interview is dedicated to a description of the collection of the Whiting-Robertsdale Historical Society, the curator of which is Mrs. Gehrke. The Gehrkes discuss World War I, the Great Depression, and World War II in Whiting, as well as Standard Oil, the area's foremost employer and business. In addition, they comment on various local businesses, the industrial modernization that occurred in the nineteen fifties, and the 1955 fire at Standard Oil.
  Whiting, Indiana; Danger Keep Out; 1955 Standard Oil fire; Great Depression; industrial modernization; local artifacts; local business; local politics; pollution; World War I; World War II; Standard Oil Company; Whiting-Robertsdale Historical Society; Mostil, Johnny; Mullins, M.L.
- Gima, Marguerite, November 9, 1990; 91-007; Bodnar, John; 46 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 110 minutes; index
  Marguerite Gima, born in 1915, discusses her parents' emigration to America, her family, the ethnic division in Whiting, Indiana, and the changes that have taken place in Whiting over the years. She discusses her family's values, the changing importance attributed to the attainment of American citizenship, and the impact of the Great Depression, World War II, and the Vietnam War on her family and on Whiting. In addition, she recalls Whiting community life and the centrality of the Fourth of July Parade in Whiting in years past.
  East Chicago, Illinois; Hammond, Indiana; American citizenship; Arabs; community life; emigration; employee benefits; ethnic diversity; family values; Fourth of July; Great Depression; Greek Orthodox church; local business; pollution; Tourism; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; women's movement; World War II; American Legion; American Maize; Greek Catholic Union of the USA; Standard Oil Company; Kopcha, Joseph
- Grenchik, Philip J., August 19, 1992; 91-168; Orr, Lisa; 26 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 78 minutes; index
  Philip J. Grenchik, born in 1938, speaks of his family and life in Whiting, Indiana, giving special emphasis to the history of banking and his career in banking there. He discusses the difficulty in purchasing housing in Whiting because of the stable number of houses and the extremely limited possibility of expansion. In addition, Mr. Grenchik comments on the hidden wealth of Whiting's citizens, largely blue collar workers with strong work ethics who often bought Standard Oil stock and lived frugally. He also discusses the demographic diversity of the Whiting community.
  banker; Gary, Indiana; banking; ethnic diversity; real estate; work ethic; American Trust and Savings Bank; AMOCO; Whiting Community Center
- Gresko, Joseph, May 14, 1991; 91-023; Bodnar, John; 38 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 74 minutes; index